Syntax and runtime errors also occur when
trying to retrieve data from a database.
Here is a query that will attempt to retrieve
information from a database.
When I execute it, we get a syntax error near
the FROM keyword.
Upon further inspection, we see something
common to queries, a misplacement of commas.
The usual reason for this is that a column
was located after this Status column.
It was removed, but the comma was never replaced.
One solution to the problem is always to ensure
there is no comma after the last column listed
in a query.
Here is a tip for using commas that will make
the previous issue never happen.
It's actually a tip I got from a coworker
long ago: Put the commas at the beginning
of each line after the first line.
I will do that and remove the commas from
the ends of the lines, execute the statement,
and the query now works.
Let us now see an example of a runtime error.
With management applications such as SQL Server
Management Studio, one could be working with
multiple databases.
Sometimes, someone could be trying to run
a well-written query but against the wrong
database.
I am purposely going to switch databases and
then try to execute this query.
Of course, it will not work because the query
is running against the wrong database.
What is worse is to have two copies of a database,
such as a production copy and a test copy,
and run an action query, such as an UPDATE,
INSERT, or DELETE query against the wrong
database.
One way to solve this problem is to utilize
a USE statement at the beginning of a query.
I will add, to the top of this query, the
statement USE AdventureWorks2019.
Then, when I execute this, everything runs.
The Available Databases field updates as well.